From Idaho Capitol Sun, Idaho Budget Committee introduces new health and welfare budget with
additional cuts.
Idaho Budget Committee introduces new health and welfare budget with additional cuts.
New state budget intended to replace budget that Idaho Senate rejected on March 12th.
By Clark Corbin, March 19th, 2026, 5-8 p.m.
The exterior of the Idaho Statehouse.
The exterior of the Idaho Statehouse, as seen on March 16th, 2026, in Boise, photo by Pat
Sutphin for the Idaho Capitol Sun.
The Idaho Legislature's Budget Committee introduced a new health and human services budget Thursday
that includes $21 million in additional budget cuts to Medicaid disability services.
Get the morning headlines.
The new budget replaces the original fiscal year 2027 health and human services maintenance
of operations budget, which the Idaho Senate killed on March 12th.
Senators killed the original budget following an impassioned debate from Jim Guthrie, R.
McCammon.
The new health and human services budget introduced Thursday includes one change from the original
budget the Senate killed.
The new budget reduces funding by an additional $21 million in connection with House Bill
863.
House Bill 863 is a separate bill that would cut provider rates for residential habilitation
programs.
That bill advanced out of the Senate Health and Welfare Committee on Wednesday, the Idaho
Capitol Sun previously reported.
Reducing funding for the services will cause the state to miss out on an additional $44
million in federal funds, according to state budget documents.
That brings the total cost of the funding reduction to $65 million after the lost federal
funds are calculated.
The fiscal year 2027 health and human services maintenance budget includes funding for the
Idaho Department of Health and Welfare and the Independent Living Council.
Idaho Republicans, Governor have pushed for state budget cuts throughout 2026 session.
Budget cuts have been the defining and some of the most controversial elements of the
2026 legislative session.
Governor Brad Little and the Idaho Legislature are cutting budget cuts for most state agencies.